<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The information of Capt. Hen. Wilkinson of what hath passed betwixt him and some other persons, who have attempted to prevail with him to swear high treason against the Earl of Shaftsbury. Together with the confirmation of Major Jarvis James, to whom he daily communicated the particulars.</title>
            <author>Wilkinson, Henry, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66064</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224077</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834631</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834631</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39135</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66064)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39135)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1821:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The information of Capt. Hen. Wilkinson of what hath passed betwixt him and some other persons, who have attempted to prevail with him to swear high treason against the Earl of Shaftsbury. Together with the confirmation of Major Jarvis James, to whom he daily communicated the particulars.</title>
                  <author>Wilkinson, Henry, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6, 5-7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Henry Wilkinson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text and register continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Magdalen College Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, --  Earl of, 1621-1683 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39135:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE INFORMATION OF Capt. Hen. Wilkinſon, OF What hath paſſed betwixt him and ſome other Perſons, who have attempted to prevail with him to SWEAR HIGH TREASON AGAINST THE Earl of Shaftsbury.</p>
            <p>Together with the CONFIRMATION OF MAJOR <hi>JARVIS JAMES,</hi> To whom he daily Communicated the PARTICULARS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Wilkinſon,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:39135:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39135:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have given you account of ſome. Paſſages ſince my unexpected Retirement to this Place, the <hi>King's-Bench,</hi> where I am under a ſtricter Confinement than any other Perſon, upon what Account, or by what Order, I know not: For want of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency and place of Retirement, I cannot give the Particulars in ſo good Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod and Order as the thing requires. If I had received the Privilege of going abroad, as other Perſons, who ſtand, I believe, under worſe Circumſtances, I ſhould have made bold firſt to acquaint His Majeſty, before I had publiſhed this to the World: But upon inquiry, Why I am thus cloſely confined? I have met with various Reports from the Officers that belong to this Place, to my Fellow-Priſoners, who often bring me in ſtrange Reports, and dreadful News; that is, That I am ſure to be hang'd for things I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned againſt the Government. By ſome it's reported, I am that Perſon that was intended to murder His Majeſty. To vindicate my ſelf and my Innocency, I am forc'd to publiſh this, and to let the World know, That, I bleſs God, I am not in the leaſt afraid of what can befall me. I do by this bid Defiance to all Mankind, to charge me with any Diſloyalty againſt my King and Country: If I periſh, it ſhall be for ſpeaking and declaring Truth; which the World may judge, is without expectation of Reward or Applauſe... I only deſire to live and die an Honeſt <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> and to leave my ſelf and Family without Diſgrace. I am reſolv'd never to procure my Inlargement or an Eſtate to entail a Curſe upon my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily: I am not ſo much in love with the World, or an Eſtate as ſome others, that deſire to have an Eſtate upon any Account; beſides, I have ſpent the prime of my days, and cannot expect long to enjoy it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>HENRY WILKINSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>I Having had (in the late unhappy Civil War) the honour of ſerving His late Majeſty of bleſſed Memory, and his moſt Glorious Majeſty King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, in a good Capacity, under ſeveral Qualifications, in <hi>England</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, in which I acquitted my ſelf as a Gentleman and Loyal Subject: yet (with many others in the ſame Service) had the misfortune to be much impoveriſhed, and impriſoned in <hi>England</hi> and beyond Sea.</p>
            <p>That when the good Providence of God had reſtored His preſent Majeſty to His Crowns and Government, I was to my utmoſt inſtrumental, as became my Duty ſo to do; and alſo did riſe with the Gentry of <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> who ſecured <hi>York</hi> when Major General <hi>Lambert</hi>'s Army fac'd and put a ſtop to the Army of General <hi>Monk:</hi> The Force we then made with our ſelves and Servants, and the ſecuring of <hi>York,</hi> was the cauſe of breaking and diſſipating the Army of Major General <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert;</hi> which gave a good opportunity for General <hi>Monk</hi> to march.</p>
            <p>That ſeeing how difficult, and how almoſt impoſſible it was for His Majeſty to gratifie all ſuch who were then in expectation of, or wanted His Royal Bounty; I rather choſe to betake my ſelf to ſuch juſt and honourable Means, for Support of my ſelf and Family, as did occur to me, than to depend upon, or apply my ſelf unto the Court for an Employment: And did thereupon engage in, and enter upon ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Affairs and Managements of good and rational Proſpects. But ſuch was my misfortune, or elſe of thoſe I was concerned with, as that all prov'd not only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsful, but oft to my great loſs. I have alſo ſpent above a thouſand Pounds at Court, in aſſiſting Mr. <hi>Caſtillian Morris,</hi> Son to Colonel <hi>John Morris</hi> who was Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Pontefract</hi>-Caſtle, who was hang'd, drawn, and quarter'd for his Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; in which Garriſon I was, and after with His Majeſty beyond Sea.</p>
            <p>That I having for above twenty years thus ſpent my time and pains in fruitleſs Endeavours, I left the County of <hi>York,</hi> my uſual Reſidence and place of Birth, and with my Family came to <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At length having intimation that conſiderable Encouragements would be given to ſuch as would Tranſport themſelves and Families to <hi>Carolina,</hi> I took a reſolution
<pb facs="tcp:39135:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo to do, with what ſmall Fortune I had left, reſolving to bid Adieu to my own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind Country.</p>
            <p>That in purſuance of theſe Reſolutions, I waited on the Lords Proprietors, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from them perſonally the State of the ſaid Country, and the particular En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements to be given; of all which I received a full and ſatis factory Account. And having the Honour to be well known, with my Service and Sufferings, unto the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Craven</hi> then preſent, his Lordſhip was pleaſed to ſay, He was ſatisfied of my Honeſty and Integrity; and for my better encouragement, freely offered me to go thither in quality of their Governour over the North-part of the ſaid Country: which unexpected Favour I kindly accepted, and ſome time after had a Patent conſtituting me ſuch; as alſo one other, for one of my Sons to be Surveyor-General of the ſame; alſo, for my youngeſt Son to be Regiſter.</p>
            <p>That during the negotiating this Affair, I had frequent occaſion to wait upon and become acquainted with the Lords Proprietors, and amongſt the reſt with the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> from whom I had always a very kind Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; but never had with his Lordſhip any other Diſcourſe than was occaſional, in relation to my intended Voyage.</p>
            <p>To which having thus engaged my ſelf, I made all the neceſſary Preparations; and in the Month of <hi>April</hi> laſt hired the Ship <hi>Abigail</hi> of <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> Burthen One hundred and thirty Tuns, or thereabouts, whereof was Maſter <hi>Thomas Wood;</hi> which Ship I Victualled for the ſaid Maſter, ten Men, and alſo for all ſuch Paſſengers as ſhould be taken on board.</p>
            <p>And put on board all my Houſhold-goods, and ſuch other Neceſſaries as was proper, as alſo my Wife, Daughter, and three Sons, (two of which had the honour to ſerve his Majeſty, one being a Commiſſion-Officer ſome years at Sea) together with above thirty Servants, women and men, the men of all ſorts of different Mechanick Trades, with their neceſſary Utenſils; as alſo ſeveral perſons, and ſome Families, who had contracted with me for themſelves and their Goods, paſſage and fraight, who were on board; and ſeveral others promiſed to ſhip themſelves and Goods, but did not.</p>
            <p>Amongſt which was one Mr. <hi>Booth,</hi> whom I had known above twenty years in the North of <hi>England,</hi> and to be a perſon of good Learning, and very inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, but under the Character of a very ill Reputation: This Gentleman and his Family, then reſiding in <hi>Salisbury-Court,</hi> hearing of my intended Voyage, appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf unto me, and with great proteſtations declared, that for the future he would reform his Life and Converſation both towards God and towards Man, and would ſhip himſelf and Family, with what number of Servants he could: Which Propoſals being early, did encourage me to hire the ſaid Ship ſooner than other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I intended, he promiſing to put on board to the number of ſixteen perſons of his own Family.</p>
            <p>By which means, and others failure, together with ſome difficulties which I met with, the ſaid Ship lay in the River ſo long, with ſuch Servants and Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers aboard her, at my ſole charge, as forced me to contract more Debts than I expected: Alſo I was in great trouble, and was much detain'd by reaſon of ſome Debts I was bound for, and fell upon me. And intending juſt and full ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou to all men, and to ſupply my ſelf with all things neceſſary in order thereto, was the occaſion of my having the ſaid Ship ſo long upon charges, <hi>viz.</hi> from the month of <hi>April</hi> until <hi>Auguſt</hi> following; at which time, having gone through moſt of the difficulties I ſtrugled under, I reſolved to ſail in three or four days.</p>
            <p>But a Gentleman who was one of the Freightors, and a Paſſenger, looking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf injur'd by the long demurrage of the Ship, arreſted me; and next day after, ſeveral others did the like; which threw me into the Compter in <hi>Wood-ſtreet,</hi> where I made fair and reaſonable offers of ſatisfaction; but through the ſtubbornneſs of the perſons concern'd, the ſaid Propoſals proved ineffectual.</p>
            <p>Upon which, my Servants on board, though in Covenant, and long maintain'd at my Charge, went from the ſaid Ship, as did alſo the Paſſengers with their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Goods, to my exceeding great loſs; beſides that of my Place and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and beſides the loſs of all my own Goods and Eſtate.</p>
            <p>That being under theſe unhappy complicated Misfortunes, I removed my ſelf by <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> to the Priſon of the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> on or about the 17th day of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> laſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>HENRY WILKINSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:39135:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Information of Capt. <hi>Henry Wilkinſon,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IMprimis,</hi> I the ſaid <hi>Henry Wilkinſon</hi> do declare, and am ready to ſwear, That on Saturday <hi>Octob.</hi> the 8. 1681. about five a Clock in the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, one Mr. <hi>Walter Bains</hi> came to Mr. <hi>Adams</hi> Cellar in the Kings-bench Priſon, and ſent for me out of the Garden in the Kings-Bench; who upon ſight, told me, he way ſorry to ſee me in that place; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards engaged me to accept of a Pot of Beer or Ale: In the time of its drinking, Mr. <hi>Baines</hi> ſhewed and expreſſed the greateſt Kindneſs that could be expected from a Brother, which made me believe he had ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. Then he deſired to know what ſort of Wine I would drink, I told him, not any; beſides the Cellar had none; but he called then for Brandy, which we had. Then he told me Mr. <hi>Brownrig</hi> was ſent Priſoner to <hi>York</hi> Caſtle for Treaſon, and for appearing for my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury:</hi> And alſo the ſaid <hi>Baines</hi> ſaid, he had ſent a Note to my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> to demand Fifty ſhillings for Service and Charges that was due to him, done for the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> at my requeſt, as he pretends; and that my Lord ſent him word, it was a ſham and a cheat put upon him, therefore would pay him no ſuch Bill.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time he told me, I could not but know much of the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s Deſigns againſt the King; and that I might do well to diſcover it to him, who was ready to do me any kindneſs, and deſired an opportunity. Alſo, that he had been lately with Mr. <hi>Graham:</hi> And that he hath great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt with my Lord <hi>Hyde,</hi> (all this time I underſtood what was deſigning for my kindneſs). I conſtantly and truly told him, I knew nothing of my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s deſigns againſt his Majeſty; onely this I did know formerly from Mr. <hi>Baines</hi> about three Months ago, that he was then of an opinion that Mr. <hi>Brownrig</hi> could diſcover ſome unlawful practices againſt the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> which, I confeſs, I did wiſh might be diſcovered; for although I have ſerved his Majeſty in <hi>England,</hi> and beyond Sea, (and no other intereſt) and as inſtrumental in his Majeſties Reſtauration as any perſon of my fortune could be, ſo I am for his continuance by all lawful means, and never to ſtudy the deſtruction of his Friends or Enermies by unjuſt deſigns. I have cauſe to believe my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> loves his Majeſtie; for he always was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſhew me reſpect for that I had ſerved his Majeſtie.</p>
            <p>Now night drew on for Mr. <hi>Baines</hi> to be gone; all the time he ſtaid was ſpent with a great deal of Zeal upon me on the ſame Subject: He told me I ſhould have a Pardon, and need not to fear it; I would not deny his profer. But he further told me, I ſhould be conſiderably rewarded; neither did I deny that, but told, when I was requited for my former, I would ſerve his Majeſtie in what I could. I ſee here was a Deſign laid, although I had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to take it unkindly to have any thing fixt upon me, or to make me an inſtrument beyond my knowledge, yet I was reſolved to humour the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Upon which Mr. <hi>Baines</hi> took his leave this night, and told me at par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, he would in a few days ſee me again; but left me with ſuch promiſes as at preſent I cannot expreſs, not much queſtioning my Knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> That on Tueſday <hi>October</hi> the 11th 1681. I was ſent for to Mr. <hi>Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi>'s houſe near the Kings Bench, to Mr. <hi>Booth,</hi> who told me he was glad to ſee me, but ſorry to ſee us both in that condition, for he was a Priſoner as I was; he told me he had removed himſelf laſt night from one of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pters. I required of him how he came to be at a Waiters houſe? He told me it was not denied him, although I could not be admitted one night. I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39135:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>underſtood he was engaged in the Deſign; I conſidered he had been a man of bad Principles, therefore was reſolved to ſland upon my guard. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently he told me, he was to tell me I had an opportunity to be a better man in my fortune than ever I was before; and that now I had an opportunity to make my Fortune: And that I might have Five hundred pounds <hi>per An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> ſetled upon me and my Heirs, or Ten thouſand pound in Money, which I pleaſed, if I would diſcover what I knew of my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> and his deſign in changing the Government to a Commonwealth, and witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. I replied and told him, no body would believe I ſhould be made privie to ſuch a Deſign, (if ſuch a thing was) being I had ſerved his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie in <hi>England</hi> and beyond Sea. He anſwered, I was the likelieſt man to know; for he knew I had ſerved the King, and had been ſlighted and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected. I told him that was true. I anſwered him again, I never deſired any thing of his Majeſtie for my Service, but that which would coſt him nothing; but onely have the preference of others, that never had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in his Majeſties ſervice, by way of farm on part of his Majeſties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues: He told me his Majeſtie knew me, and that he was ſenſible of my Service and Sufferings, and deſired to gratifie me; for he often told me, now was the time to do ſomething which would advance me; for it muſt now be a King or a Commonwealth: For the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s Party would but onely make uſe of me, to ſlight me when their buſineſs was done. I told him, I was with my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> the night before he was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and that Sir <hi>Thomas Armſtrong</hi> was there, a perſon I knew out of favour, on purpoſe that he might ſpeak out his full mind; but ſtill told him, I knew nothing of any deſign: I alſo told him, I would ſay nothing, nor appear at Court, until I was conſidered for my ſufferings; (a thing I never expected) and as for going to Court, I never intended it; but the more I told him I knew nothing of a Deſign, the more he put me in mind of what Reward I might have, in ſuch words that I ought to Swear it, whether I knew any thing or nothing of the buſineſs. Now I fully ſaw the Deſign; and although I ſtaid late, at my return I began to conſider who I ſhould make this buſineſs and deſign known to, being a ſtranger in the <hi>Kings Bench;</hi> I obſerved one who appeared to me to be a ſober and ſenſible perſon; that night I repaired to him, and (leſt I ſhould be tempted with what offers were made) I told him, that I had a deſign to commit a Secret to him; Whereupon I told him, and deſired him to put the ſame in Writing; and that if ever I declared more than what I did then to him, (that was) That I know nothing of any Plot or Deſign againſt his Majeſtie intended by my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi> I told him this, and declared it in the preſence of God; and if ever I ſhould be tempted to Swear more than this at any time, it was for Reward; and that I deſired him to witneſs the truth of this againſt me; and that I would daily give him an account of what paſſed for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which I deſired him every day to put down in Writing, which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live he hath done; as alſo the the conſtant Invitations abroad, and the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits they gave me here, which were ſo frequent to me, as nothing could be more.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> told me, I muſt appear at Court, and I ſhould have an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of my Reward from ſome perſons of Honour: I told him, I would not truſt any Courtier I knew, for a Groat; I am ſatisfied he was put upon this, but by whom, God knows, I am aſſured not by his Majeſtie.</p>
            <p>That on Wedneſday <hi>Octob.</hi> the 12th, 1681. I was invited by Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> to dine with him that day at Mr. <hi>Weaver</hi>'s houſe; which I refuſed, (although he ſent a Waiter, and promiſed him ſatisfaction for his attendance.) After
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39135:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Dinner he ſent again: I went, and found Mr. <hi>Baines</hi> with him, both riſing from Dinner: I was moſt kindly received with Wine and good words, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king upon me to come in a Witneſs againſt my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s deſigning to change the Government; declaring, I had an opportunitie to make my Familie and Friends, as they had expreſt formerly. I told them, as I had done before, Until I was ſatisfied for by-paſt Services, I would not be concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned any way at Court. They told me, I might be aſſured of what I would deſire from my Lord <hi>Hallifax</hi> and my Lord <hi>Hyde.</hi> Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> required what would ſatisfie me: I told him, If they would give me two thouſand Guineys towards the injurie I had received, and my Friends upon my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, I would diſcover what I knew. Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> told me, a greater thing was intended me; for I was intended five hundred pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> or ten thouſand pounds in money: But I ſtill told them, I knew nothing of any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne by my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi> The more I declared I knew nothing, the more Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> urged the Reward. I told him (when he was ſo earneſt) when I had the money, and a general Pardon, I would then do any ſervice I could; but I would not truſt the promiſes of Courtiers. Mr. <hi>Baines</hi> told me, As to a Pardon, I might have it in two or three days: He deſired to know my Chriſtian name, which I conceived was with an intention to get a Pardon; a thing never in my thoughts, but Mr. <hi>Baines</hi> formerly mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to me; and truly I did not know what I might ſtand in need of, or what they would fix upon me in our diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Baines</hi> told me, he had the night before been with my Lord <hi>Hallifax</hi> and Lord <hi>Hyde:</hi> now they thought they had prevailed with me, and were mightie chearful. Before I parted from them, my Wife coming to me, told me, Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> had been mightie urgent with her, to engage me to come in a Witneſs; and then told her, I ſhould have five hundred pounds <hi>per Annum</hi> ſettled upon me: But what grounds he had for this, I know not; for all perſons that know her, know her to be a perſon of unqueſtionable Repute. Nor did I queſtion the performance; for I thought what I could ſay, would not deſerve it: neither could I tell, why they ſhould think me ſuch a man, as they would have me to be; for I ever hated to be a Witneſs or a Jurie-man all my time. I conceive Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> thought I might be wrought upon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I had great misfortunes, and that this was a readie way to repair me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Octob.</hi> the 13th, 1681. This day I had a Waiter ſent me, about eleven a clock, to deſire me to go to Mr. <hi>Weaver</hi>'s houſe; which I did: There was Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baines.</hi> who told me, they ſent for me to dine with them. I had no deſire to have any Table-talk with them; I deſired to be excuſed, and alſo promiſed to ſee them after dinner. Mr. <hi>Baines</hi> told me, Mr. <hi>Graham</hi> was not far off, and would be there; and that he was ſent by ſome of the Council to diſcourſe me. Mr. <hi>Baines</hi> told me, on Tueſday-night he was at Court with my Lord <hi>Hallifax</hi> and Lord <hi>Hyde,</hi> and the two Secretaries of State, and that they enquired who knew me: He replied, Mr. <hi>Graham,</hi> who was ſent for: they askt him as to my Reputation: they askt him if he knew me, and how long: He ſaid, About twentie years: They enquired of him concerning me. He told me, Mr. <hi>Graham</hi> anſwered, I had ſerved his Majeſtie and his Father in <hi>England</hi> and beyond Sea faithfully, and that I was a very honeſt man; and alſo that I was a great Sufferer, and that I had received great Diſappointments, and had been ill dealt with by ſome that belonged to the Court, as in particular, Mr. <hi>Edward Progers;</hi> and that they engaged Mr. <hi>Graham</hi> to come over to the <hi>Kings-bench,</hi> and to aſſure me, that I ſhould be requited for my Sufferings: Alſo to take me over with him to the King, where I ſhould have the Promiſe of his Majeſtie for the ſame, and the opportunitie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39135:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>to declare my former Grievances, and receive his Royal Word and Promiſe for my Reward and Sufferings. After this Diſcourſe, Mr. <hi>Graham</hi> came in, who told me the ſame things as above, and that I might be aſſured of thoſe things from the King; alſo that he had an Order to carrie me to his Majeſtie. I told him, I could ſay nothing, neither would I go to <hi>Whitehal;</hi> for I had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a Reſolution againſt going to <hi>Whitehal:</hi> it was hard preſſed for my go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thither. I deſired to be excuſed; for if I could ſay any thing, I muſt be guiltie my ſelf: But he told me, Whether I was or not, I might be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced for my Sufferings: Upon which I took my leave, and went away not well pleaſed, that for my requital I ſhould be thought an ill man, or a Traitor.</p>
            <p>That on <hi>October</hi> the Fourteenth, 1681. Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> came to me about eleven a clock, to the <hi>Kings-bench:</hi> We walk'd in the Garden about an hour: His buſineſs was, to know my mind, whether I would go voluntarily to the King, or not. He alſo told me, that Mr. <hi>Wilſon,</hi> my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s Secretarie, that was in the <hi>Gatehouſe,</hi> had ſent to the Council to inform them, That if he might have his Pardon, he would come in, and declare his Knowledge; and therefore he would have me to have the honour to be the firſt Diſcoverer. I told him, I had no buſineſs at <hi>Whitehal.</hi> Then he told me, it was intended that Mr. <hi>Graham</hi> ſhould be at his Lodging this Afternoon, to ſee if I would go to the King; if not, my Lord Chief Juſtice Warrant would be ſent to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel me to appear at his Chamber, where there would be ſome of the Council to examine me and ſwear me. He alſo told me, that the Duke of <hi>York</hi> had a great Eſtate in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that he would give me five hundred pounds <hi>per Annum</hi> there, beſides all former Promiſes, to be ſetled upon me and my Heirs, if I would come in a Witneſs againſt my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi> I told him, they might meet with many perſons in this Age, that would accept of ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers. I told him, if I had any thing to ſay, it was the moſt proper time in Court, for me and Witneſſes to ſpeak their Knowledge. I told him, I did not know but the preſence of a King and his Promiſes, might make a man ſay more than what was true, or than he could ſay fairly in a Court. Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> ask'd me, if I did not ride with my Sword and Piſtols out of Town with my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> when he went to <hi>Oxford?</hi> I told him I did; I could not do leſs than wait upon him out of Town, who had been ſo kind, with the reſt of the Lords Proprietors, to do me the honour to make me their Governour for the Countrie of <hi>Carolina.</hi> He then told me, I muſt needs be privie to this, <hi>That if his Majeſty would not paſs three Acts, One for Excluding the Duke of</hi> York; <hi>the next, for making void the Act of Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>against Recuſancy; and a third, for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niting Proteſtant Subjects; then by force of Arms he was to be compelled.</hi> He told me, all the Council was ſatisfied I knew this, and as much as any perſon, in regard that both my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> and my ſelf was diſguſted at Court. He ſaid, the Council knew I was a Souldier, and was ſatisfied I was to act in that Concern. I begun now to conſider what a Fortune was now promis'd, and what a good Addition this five hundred pounds Additional from the Duke of <hi>York</hi> would make to the former Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And after he was gone, I acquainted my Wife, and told her how great a perſon ſhe was like to be: But this was no News to her; for Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> had often been deſiring her, for her own good, to engage me in this honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Service. Thus theſe things in our Troubles ſerved us to be merrie with, to conſider how eaſily we were like to leap into an Eſtate: But all this time we was not without fear and danger of enjoying it, or any part of it, much leſs of intailing it upon our Poſteritie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Octob.</hi> 15. 1681. This day, about eleven a clock, Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> came again to me to the <hi>Kings-bench,</hi> to know if I yet would go to <hi>Whitehal:</hi> I demanded. For what? He told me, To Evidence againſt the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi> I told him, I had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39135:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>to ſay againſt him. He importuned me not to loſe this great Opportunity I now had. Before we parted, Mr. <hi>Baines</hi> came to us; I deſired to know why they ſhould be ſo urgent to have me a Witneſs. He told me, there were none but <hi>Iriſh</hi> Witneſſes yet to come againſt my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and they were not Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Credit; but if I would come in, although I had been unfortunate in my Private Concerns, yet I was not blemiſh'd in my Credit. Mr. <hi>Baines</hi> told me, if I would not go to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> the Marſhal had a <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> from my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Pemberton,</hi> to carry me. So we parted.</p>
            <p>About Four a Clock in the afternoon, the Marſhal came with Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baines,</hi> to require me to go along with him. I demanded, Whither? He told me to <hi>Whitehall.</hi> I demanded to ſee his Warrant. He ſhew'd it me. Now I was forced to obey. After my comming thither, in a little time I was called in to Mr. Secretary <hi>Jenkins</hi>'s Office, where he and my Lord <hi>Conway</hi> was, who ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but very fairly and honeſtly, Examined me about my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and what I knew of any Deſign againſt his Majeſty. I told them, as I did to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Attackers, I knew nothing. Great Arguments were uſed; but I could give no ſatisfactory Anſwer, as was (I conceived) expected. After this His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty came into the Office: When He ſaw me, He was pleaſed to do me the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to ſay, He knew me well, and that I had ſerved His Father and His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty faithfully, and He hoped I would not decline my Obedience. To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, I never deſerved to be ſuſpected. His Majeſly was pleaſed to tell me, He had not had the Opportunity to ſerve His Friends, but hoped He might: He was pleaſed to promiſe to conſider for me my Sufferings. Then His Majeſty began to Examine me, (if I had been exhorted by the beſt Divine in <hi>England,</hi> he could not have ſaid more than His Majeſty) in telling me, what Kindneſs was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended me, was not with a deſign to invite me to ſpeak a Word but Truth it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and that if He knew I did, or any Perſon, His Majeſty would never endure them. Then His Majeſty demanded, What I knew of a Deſign againſt His Perſon and Government? I truly told His Majeſty, That I knew nothing of any Plot or Deſign againſt His Majeſty or Government; That I admired why I ſhould be ſuſpected, that had ſerved His Majeſty and His Father in <hi>England</hi> and beyond-Sea, and was as Inſtrumental as any Perſon in His Majeſties Reſtorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But ſome Perſons had poſſeſſed His Majeſty, I was deep in ſome Deſign againſt the Government, and knew much of my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury:</hi> So His Majeſty ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to be ſatisfied, but ſtill preſſed hard upon me. To all His Majeſties Queſtions, I could give no Anſwer that would ſatisfie. Then his Majeſty was pleaſed to tell me, If I would ſay, <hi>As I hope to be ſaved, I knew nothing of any Deſign againſt His Perſon,</hi> He would believe me; which I did ſay, in thoſe very Words: which His Majeſty ſeemed to wonder at. Then I was leſt to Mr. Secretary <hi>Jenkins,</hi> who was pleaſed to uſe ſuch arguments as he thought fit. I told him, I knew my Duty to His Majeſty, I would not draw a Sword againſt Him; but I could freely do it againſt ſome of the Court, that were Enemies to His Majeſty and his Friends; and ſo I was diſmiſs'd out of the Office. Then I was carried into another Room, where His Majeſty, my Lord Chancellor, Lord <hi>Hallifax,</hi> Lord <hi>Hyde,</hi> the two Secretaries of State was, and the Lord Chief-Juſtice <hi>Pemberton:</hi> Where I was Examined, Mr. <hi>Graham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Booth,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baines</hi> preſent. My Lord Chancellor was ſharp upon me with ſeveral Queſtions, which I could give no Anſwer to. Content thus I was to run the Gantlet from one Place to another. My Lord Chancellor would not believe but I muſt be guilty of knowing great things againſt my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi> I told him, If I could not be believed upon my Word there, if they pleaſed to bring my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> upon his Trial, I would declare it in open Court upon Oath what my Knowledge was, without any hopes of Gain or Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. My Lord Chancellor, I thank him, he did me that Equity, to tell me, There were Two ſorts of Advancements; I need not give my ſelf that trouble, for I was like to come to my Trial my ſelf before my Lord <hi>Shaftſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</hi> My Lord Chancellor demanded of me, If I had no Comiſſion for this New Service againſt His Majeſty. I told him, No. Then he told me, I was to have a Troop to conſiſt of Fifty men. I told him, that was a ſmall Troop; I hoped, that if ever I had a Command of a Troop, it ſhould be a better than that: but I deſired to know who gave that Information. He told me, Mr. <hi>Booth,</hi> who was (by, and was) liſted under me. I deſired Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> to tell me if he had given this Information, and made this Oath? He told me, Yes, and it was true. I was unconcerned, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39135:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>am, knowing my ſelf not guilty: for I proteſt, in the preſence of Almighty God, by whom I expect to be judged, I never had a word with Mr. <hi>Booth,</hi> or any other Perſon, in my whole Life, tending to any ſuch thing: For at the ſame time that he ſaid this was to be, which was when the Parliament was to be laſt at <hi>Oxford,</hi> I had taken on a Ship for <hi>Carolina,</hi> where I was to go Governour, a Buſineſs more to my content than any Military Employ, eſpecially againſt His Majeſty and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But I conceived this was in hopes of Reward, and to ſhew his Loyalty; for which, I believe, he will neither be regarded nor rewarded. I told the Council, if they had ſuch another Witneſs, they might do my buſineſs. I thank God, I am not afraid of him, nor Twenty more ſuch Witneſſes, if they come againſt me; for 'tis well known, he hath been accuſed and condemned for Clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and Coining, beſides Murder; for which he had His Majeſties Gracious Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, as I have been informed. I am glad I live in ſuch days, wherein Juries con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they are Judges as to matter of Fact; for, if they were not, I am ſatisfied, in this Swearing Age, many an honeſt Man would be forced to march before they know either Rank or File. At the ſame time I told my Lord Chancellor, If any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Man would come and witneſs againſt me, I would never deſire His Majeſties Pardon, or ever will. Let all the World judge how unlikely it is, that I ſhould be thus concerned, when I had about Twenty eight Men ſervants, Four or Five Women-ſervants, beſides my Wife, Three Sons, (of which, Two had been in His Majeſties Service at Sea,) and one Daughter, all the Children I have, prepared, and lay at my Charge, intending for <hi>Carolina</hi> and thought my ſelf happy, and was reſolved to leave <hi>England,</hi> with reſolution to ſee if I could find a People that had leſs Wit and more Honeſty than I have found in my own Country; where, I muſt needs ſay, I have found very unfaithful Dealings amongſt ſuch as account them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Perſons of Honour and Quality: But truly, when I thought I had made my ſelf almoſt ready for my intended Voyage, I found my ſelf like a man bewitched, that could neither budge nor ſtir; until at laſt ſome Debts that I was bound for fell upon me, and others of my own encreaſed, being burthened with a great Charge, which unexpectedly put a ſtop, at preſent, to my intended Voyage. I did always intend to leave <hi>England</hi> Honeſtly and Honourably: Thoſe things fell ſo unexpectedly, that my ſelf and Wife concluded there was a Divine hand in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Information of</hi> Jarvis James <hi>Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I <hi>Jarvis James</hi> Gent. do declare, That the above-named Captain <hi>Henry Wilkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> came to me upon <hi>Tueſday</hi> the Eleventh of <hi>October,</hi> 1681. in the Evening, and did then, and likewiſe every day from time to time afterwards, make me acquainted with the ſeveral Treaties and Tranſactions between him the ſaid Captain <hi>Henry Wilkinſon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baines,</hi> Mr. <hi>Booth,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Graham,</hi> and the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Perſons in this his Information mentioned; and that they were the very ſame in ſubſtance with what he hath herein ſet forth and declared: for at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and my own ſatisfaction, I kept a daily Journal during the time of their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. All which ſhall be atteſted upon Oath when required.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Information of Mrs.</hi> Suſannah Wilkinſon, <hi>Wife of</hi> Henry Wilkinſon.</p>
            <p>I The ſaid <hi>Suſannah Wilkinſon</hi> do declare, That on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the Twelfth of <hi>October,</hi> 1681. I went to the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> Priſon to ſpeak with my Husband (where I met with Three Carpenters which were entertained by him as Servants for <hi>Carolina,</hi> and who had waited a long time, and not finding him likely to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in his Voyage, they deſired to be diſcharged): but not finding him in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> I went with them to Mr. <hi>Weaver</hi>'s Houſe, where I found him in Company with Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Baines,</hi> (who were largely treating my Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band with Wine): my Husband went out to the Servants, and diſcourſed them: Then Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> took an opportunity to ſpeak to me, and told me, my Husband was a moſt obſtinate Man; and Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> deſired me to perſuade my Husband to be guided and perſuaded by him the ſaid Mr. <hi>Booth;</hi> and he ſaid, the King would do more for my Husband than ever the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> would; and that the King was ſenſible of my Husband's Service and Sufferings; and if my Husband would be perſwaded by him the ſaid <hi>Mr. Booth,</hi> to appear againſt the Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> he was ſure my Husband would be the moſt happy man in the World; and that he ſhould have Five hundred pounds a year ſetled upon him and his Heirs for ever.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:39135:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>That on <hi>Friday, October</hi> the Fourteenth, 1681. I was with my Husband at the <hi>Kings Bench</hi> Priſon, when Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> came into our Room. Mr. <hi>Booth</hi> took an opportunity to ſpeak with me, and deſired me, for Gods ſake, to perſwade my Husband to be ruled by him; which if my Husband would, he might be a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py man, and the Duke of <hi>York</hi> would ſettle Five hundred pound a year in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> upon my Husband and his Heirs; and very much intreated me to perſwade my Husband to what he deſired. All which ſhall be atteſted upon Oath when required.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Confirmation of Captain <hi>Henry Wilkinſon</hi>'s Information: By Major <hi>Jarvis James,</hi> to whom be daily and every day communicated all thoſe Particulars publiſhed in his Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the Subborning the ſaid Captain to appear a Witneſs againſt the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT hath been as well the Folly as Malice of ſome reſtleſs Perſons, ſince the publiſhing of Captain <hi>Henry Wilkinſon</hi>'s Information, to aſperſe and calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Major <hi>Jarvis James,</hi> the only Perſon to whom the Captain communicated the Important Particulars of the aboveſaid Information: But the indiſcreet Endeavours they have uſed to leſſen his Repute, doth but weaken their own. For, his Loyalty and Integrity to His Majeſty is, and hath been ſufficiently known, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving moſt faithfully, and as becomes a true Subject, ſerved His Majeſty both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea, and at home; and is again, when His Majeſty ſhall command, ready to ſerve Him to the laſt drop of his blood, with as much chearfulneſs as any Subject His Majeſty hath in His three Kingdoms.</p>
               <p>He acknowledgeth himſelf a Son of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it is by Law Eſtabliſhed; and hath accordingly, without ſcruple, taken the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, as every good Subject ought to do.</p>
               <p>He ſtiles the Acquaintance he hath with ſo deſerving a Perſon as Captain <hi>Wilkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> a great Happineſs; and acknowledgeth himſelf obliged to him, for ſo timely entruſting him with ſo notable a Secret, being a Stranger to the ſaid Captain; which Truſt he look'd upon as a great Adventure, and the Diſcovery to endanger the Lives of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> and the ſaid Captain, as his Information hath made manifeſt to the World, and which he had from his own Mouth. He likewiſe declares, before God and Man, That he believes all the ſaid Information to contain nothing but the Truth, and to be the Realities of what he had from <hi>Booth, Bains,</hi> and <hi>Graham;</hi> for he lent him the Conveniency of his Chamber to write the whole Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in, and ſaw him write it with his own Hand; as alſo may be witneſſed by Mr. <hi>Robert Bennet,</hi> who is an Officer in <hi>Leaden-hall</hi> Market, that tranſcribed it for the Captain. Such Offers as were made him, few Men (perhaps) in the Kingdom would have reſiſted, conſidering more particularly the heavy Circumſtances he lay under; encloſed in a Priſon, and having before near loſt all he had, in his intended Voyage for <hi>Carolina.</hi> In fine, Let the World conſider, and thence conclude, It was the Mercy of Almighty God that this Worthy, Noble, Loyal Gentleman, Captain <hi>Wilkinſon,</hi> had the fortune to lye under ſuch large Temptations, the Diſcovery whereof hath (I queſtion not) very much advanced the Glory of God and profited the Nation. And without doubt, His Majeſty is and will be well ſatisfied, that thoſe who faithfully and truly ſerve His Majeſty and His Subjects, are the Perſons both to be believed and relied upon. It's only deſired this may have credit accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to its Truth and Reality, both in the Heart of His Majeſty, and all His Loyal Subjects; which will anſwer the Ends of him who ſubſcribes himſelf <hi>A Well wiſher to Truth.</hi> By me</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>JARVIS JAMES.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
